Guide to the David A. Bentzin Expert Witness Files 1975-1979
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
David A. Bentzin expert witness files
1975-1979
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 815
Bentzin, David A. (David Allan), 1936-
3.5 linear feet
This collection consists of David Bentzin’s copies of reports, files, and documents related to Docket 279-D of the Indian Claims Commission case of the Blackfeet Tribe of Montana vs. The United States of America in the 1970s. Bentzin acted as an expert witness for the Blackfeet Tribe in his capacity as a petroleum exploration geologist.
Biographical Note
David Bentzin earned his Master of Science degree in Geology from the University of Montana in 1960. Upon graduation, Bentzin moved to Casper, Wyoming, where he worked as a geologist for petroleum companies. In 1975, the Blackfeet Tribe of Montana brought suit against the United States alleging that the government was deficient in its management of the tribe’s oil and gas resources. The tribe believed that the United States government had permitted the allotment of the Blackfeet Reservation to individual Native Americans without reservation of the mineral estate to the Blackfeet tribe. The tribe also alleged that the federal government had discouraged development of Blackfeet oil and gas revenues and that the government had drained oil and gas from tribal lands to non-tribal lands. David Bentzin was presented as an expert witness for the Blackfeet Tribe in his capacity as a petroleum geologist. Bentzin developed a case for the Blackfeet based on the uneven oil and gas development of the Blackfeet portion of the Cutbank Oil field by the Bureau of Indian Affairs relative to the development authorized by the Bureau of Land Management on adjacent, non-tribal parcels. The Blackfeet Tribe was eventually awarded $5 million in damages by the United States Government.
This collection consists of David Bentzin’s copies of reports, files, and documents related to Docket 279-D of the Indian Claims Commission case of the Blackfeet Tribe of Montana vs. The United States of America in the 1970s. Bentzin acted as an expert witness for the Blackfeet Tribe in his capacity as a petroleum exploration geologist. Researchers will find Bentzin’s annotations on a few reports.
This collection has been maintained in original order.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
This collection was created and maintained by the donor until time of donation to the Archives.
This collection was donated to the Archives by David Bentzin in 2008.
Montana State University-Bozeman Special Collections holds the Thomas R. Wessel Indian Claims Commission Research Papers consisting of photocopies of research reports and records from the Bureau of Indian Affairs and Department of the Interior, Indian Division gathered for Docket 279-D.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Bentzin, David A. (David Allan), 1936-Archives
United States. Bureau of Indian Affairs; United States. Indian Claims Commission; Blackfeet Tribe of the Blackfeet Indian Reservation of Montana--Claims vs. United States; Blackfeet Tribe of the Blackfeet Indian Reservation of Montana--Trials, litigation, etc.
United States--Trials, litigation, etc.
Evidence, Expert; Petroleum geologists--United States
Laws and Legislation; Montana; Native Americans
- Government Oil and Gas Report Exhibits, Docket 279-D, Indian Claims Commission, circa 1975-1979 (Box-folder 1/1-3)
- Original Defendant’s Oil and Gas Report, 1975 (Box-volume 1/4)
- Original Defendant’s Oil and Gas Report with Annotation by David Bentzin, Plaintiff’s export witness, 1975 (Box-volume 1/5)
- Defendant’s Proposed Finding of Fact, Objections to Plaintiff’s Requested Findings of Fact and Brief, circa 1975-1979 (Box-volume 2/1)
- Digest of Historian's Exhibits, Volume I, circa 1975-1979 (Box-volume 2/2)
- Digest of Historian's Exhibits, Volume II, circa 1975-1979 (Box-volume 2/3)
- A History of Economic Influences on the Fort Belknap and Blackfeet Indian Reservation, 1975 (Box-volume 2/4)
- An Historical Analysis of the Administration of the Blackfeet Indian Reservation by the United States, 1975 (Box-volume 3/1)
- Evaluation of Range Management on the Blackfeet Indian Reservation in Montana, plaintiff’s exhibit, 1975 (Box-volume 4/1)
- An Appraisal of Certain Land Dispositions and Uses on the Blackfeet Indian Reservation in Montana, Vol. I, Plaintiff’s Exhibit, 1975 (Box-volume 4/2)
- An Appraisal of Certain Land Dispositions and Uses on the Blackfeet Indian Reservation in Montana, Vol. II, Plaintiff’s Exhibit, 1975 (Box-volume 4/3)
- Plaintiff’s Requested Findings of Fact and Brief: Vol. III of VI, Oil and Gas Findings, 1978-1979 (Box-volume 4/4)
- Report Concerning Management of Oil and Gas Assets of the Blackfeet Tribe, Preliminary Report, 1975 (Box-folder 4/5)
- Report Concerning Management of Oil and Gas Assets of the Blackfeet Tribe, Final Report, 1975 (Box-folder 4/6)
- Bentzin Cross-Examination and notes, 1975 and undated (Box-folder 4/7)
- Plaintiff's Exhibit BR-18, Survey Map, circa 1975-1979 (Box-folder 4/8)
- Ashford-Raymond Cross-Examination, circa 1975-1979 (Box-folder 4/9)
- Property Accounting Report, circa 1975-1979 (Box-folder 5/1)
- Production, Cut Bank Field, circa 1975-1979 (Box-folder 5/2)
- Gas Production, Blackfeet Oil and Gas, circa 1975-1979 (Box-folder 5/3)
- Preliminary Findings of Fact, 1977 (Box-folder 5/4)
- Literature, 1975 and undated (Box-folder 5/5)
- Rebuttal, 1975 and undated (Box-folder 5/6)
- Reply to Defendant’s Objections, Blackfeet Tribal, 1979 (Box-folder 5/7)
- Reply to Defendant’s Objections, 1979 (Box-folder 6/1)
- Petitioner’s Oil and Gas Exhibits, circa 1975-1979 (Box-volume 6/2)
- Resource Lease Records, circa 1975-1979 (Box-volume 6/3)
- Plaintiff’s Exhibit BR-17 Vol. I, circa 1975-1979 (Box-volume 7/1)
- Plaintiff’s Exhibit BR-17 Vol. II, circa 1975-1979 (Box-volume 7/2)
- Plaintiff’s Exhibit BR-17 Vol. III, circa 1975-1979 (Box-volume 7/3)